let's now consider static power which is
what prevents us from lowering the
voltage too much
our transistors are really like
electronic faucets water comes here and
if the valve is open water will flow out
if the valve is closed no water but in a
transistor it's like this valve is
controlled by water pressure from
another faucet so if the power supply
voltage is dropped there is less
pressure when the faucet is closed and
as a result because there is water
pressure here and the valve is not
closed very well there will be some
leakage of water because the faucet is
not totally closed so one component of
static power is this leakage so the
problem is that as we lower the voltage
this leakage goes up so we reduce
dynamic power by lowering the voltage
but that increases the static power if
we have already lowered this voltage by
a lot then the pressure on this valve
here is relatively wimpy already if we
still lower the voltage further what's
going to happen is we're gonna get a
much larger stream of leakage here so if
we draw the voltage on the horizontal
axis and the power on the vertical axis
what we get is when the voltage is very
high
our dynamic power is also very high but
it drops quickly as we lower the voltage
so this is our dynamic power however our
leakage power is very low when the
voltage is high and it grows up very
very quickly because of the increase in
leakage as the voltage is dropped so our
total power does something like this
there is a voltage at which the overall
power is lowest if you increase the
voltage further you are spending too
much dynamic power so the overall power
goes up and you're not reducing the
static power by much anymore whereas if
you go much further down from this
voltage then the static power becomes
very large and you are no longer
reducing the dynamic power to compensate
enough for it so this is why modern
processors cannot just arbitrarily lower
the voltage to decrease the dynamic
power and also why they are starting to
have problems with static power because
we have already low
voltage to the point where the static
power becomes an issue also note that
the leakage through the transistor like
this is not the only source of leakage
that results in static power consumption
because the transistors are very small
they're acting as faucets whose valves
are now leaky too simply some water is
coming through here some of the water
that is building up the pressure is also
leaking out and so on so there are
multiple other sources for why the
static power exists but to understand
the relationship between static and
dynamic power it's sufficient to
understand that for example for voltage
dynamic power and static power are
trying to pull the voltage in opposite
direction and the optimum is somewhere
in between